<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Louise Grandjonc, Python/SQL developer but also a human</title>
    <link>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Louise Grandjonc, Python/SQL developer but also a human</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>false</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 18:39:21 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>PostgreSQL&#39;s logs - a developer&#39;s best friend</title>
      <link>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/blog/developers-and-logs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 18:39:21 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/blog/developers-and-logs/</guid>
      <description>Introduction As a developer I&amp;rsquo;ve written a lot of stupid code. And I think that if I didn&amp;rsquo;t you could make the conclusion that I don&amp;rsquo;t work much. But one example was when I was an intern at Ulule. I was working on something and the CTO asked me if I checked how many queries were executed on the page, turns out there were over a hundred&amp;hellip; I realized that I was missing some basics :</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pg_stat_statements - finding ugly queries</title>
      <link>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/blog/pg-stat-statements/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 17:39:21 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/blog/pg-stat-statements/</guid>
      <description>Introduction As a reminder, if you ended up on this page by looking up on bing pg_stat_statements, first I&amp;rsquo;m impressed, you get results with bing ? But also, this article is based on a talk that I did at the pgdayParis and here are the slides
What is pg_stat_statements ? pg_stat_statement is a postgreSQL extension, once you enable it, it tracks statistics on the queries executed by a server. It will help you find slow queries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding EXPLAIN - part 1 - Costs and actual time</title>
      <link>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/blog/explain/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 16:39:21 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/blog/explain/</guid>
      <description>Introduction If you didn&amp;rsquo;t read the articles on logs and pg_stat_statements this article is based on a talk that I did at the pgdayParis and here are the slides. The video should be online soon, you can watch the short version from the djangoConEurope 2017.
If you want to test the queries, here is the github project for the talk. You can find a dump of the database, and the SQL using generate_series to fill the DB.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding EXPLAIN - part 2 - Scans</title>
      <link>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/blog/explain-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 15:39:21 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/blog/explain-2/</guid>
      <description>Introduction If you don&amp;rsquo;t know EXPLAIN and are starting with this article, I really encourage you to start from the beginning, to understand better what a query plan is and how to use EXPLAIN. The previous article covers that.
In this article, I&amp;rsquo;m going to try to clarify the different types of scans used to filter tables and retrieve the exptected rows.
I&amp;rsquo;m here taking the example of a letter delivery system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>stephanzimmerli.com</title>
      <link>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/projects/zim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Mar 2018 22:25:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/projects/zim/</guid>
      <description>Stephan Zimmerli is an artist who has a tendancy to be brilliant in several fields: architecture, stage design, drawing, photography, music&amp;hellip; So when he came to me with the project of a website that would allow him to show his work, always in between this art forms, I was thrilled.
The website is still in construction, we are building what he calls a mnemotopy, an architecture, like a house, to visit twenty years of notebooks, music, and videos.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pgday.paris</title>
      <link>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/projects/pgday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2018 22:25:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/projects/pgday/</guid>
      <description>About three years ago, I met Dimitri Fontaine at the fosdem. He asked me to work on the pgdayParis website. He knew I was a django developer and hoped that I would be good at CSS&amp;hellip;
But working on this, helped me get into this amazing community (mostly by drinking beers the day of the deployment), use heroku for the first time and made me want to do talks. So, hurray !</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Louise Grandjonc</title>
      <link>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 17:39:21 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/about/</guid>
      <description>My name is Louise, I am a web developer. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working as a lead python developer at Ulule for three years. Previously I worked at peopledoc as a python developer. Before that I was a student at the UTC (not the timezone).
I am also working on a few sides projects, like a website for a musician, drawer, architect, the pgday paris website and a lot of unfinished experimentations (mostly for fun).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big little secrets</title>
      <link>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/secrets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 17:39:21 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/secrets/</guid>
      <description>Oh you found this page? You are a genius my friend&amp;hellip;
Here are some non-technical stuff.
For you, this video of me singing, playing the piano and the viola da gamba on one of Alela Diane song, a musician that I admire greatly &amp;lt;3
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talks and Slides</title>
      <link>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 17:39:21 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://louisegrandjonc.github.io/louisemeta.com/talks/</guid>
      <description>Upcoming talks Well none for now, though I have ideas :)
You want me to do one? Contact me on twitter or linkedin !
Past talks  pgdayParis : Becoming a better developer with EXPLAIN  Slides Video (upcoming !) You can read a serie of articles I wrote from that talk  PostgreSQL User Group Paris: A word on pgexercises.com  Slides  djangoCon 2017: The amazing world behing your ORM  Slides Video You can read the blog article from the pgdayParis one, the djangoCon talk being a short version, more ORM oriented one from the pgdayParis.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>